A Finding Aid to the Rico Lebrun Papers, 1935-1975, in the Archives of American Art AAA.lebrrico
Archives of American Art
Rico Lebrun papers
1935-1975
AAA.lebrrico
Archives of American Art
5.3 Linear feet
The papers of painter, muralist, and educator Rico Lebrun measure 5.3 linear feet and date from 1935 to 1975. Found within the papers are biographical materials; personal and business correspondence, including extensive correspondence between Lebrun and his gallery, Jacques Seligmann and Co.; writings, including illustrated notebooks; personal business records; printed material; 3 sketchbooks; and photographs of Lebrun, travels in Mexico, and his work.
Lebrun, Rico, 1900-1964
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers were donated in 1974 by Lebrun's wife, Constance Lebrun Crown. Additional materials were donated by Crown in 1976.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Constance Lebrun Crown and David Lebrun conducted by Paul Karlstrom, November 23, 1974. Syracuse University also holds papers of Rico Lebrun.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of this collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reels 2709-2714 at the Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the papers as described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm due to reprocessing.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Biographical/Historical note
Painter, muralist, and educator Rico (Frederico) Lebrun (1900-1964) lived and worked in New York City and Los Angeles, California and his modernist works were primarily influenced by traditional religious iconography and human suffering.
Born in Naples, Italy, Lebrun attended the Naples Academy of Beaux Arts after his military service in the Italian Army during WWI. He began his career as a stained glass designer and was offered a one year contract to work in Springfield, Illinois for the Pittsburgh Plate Glass Company in 1924. At the end of the contract, Lebrun moved to New York City where he found work as a commercial illustrator for magazines such as Vogue, Fortune, and The New Yorker. After a return to Italy in the early 1930s to continue his art studies, Lebrun moved to New York City in 1936 where he taught at the Art Students League, painted his first mural commission for the Fogg Art Museum with Lewis Rubenstein, and found work as an artist for the WPA.
In 1938, Lebrun moved to Southern California and accepted a position at the Chouinard Art Institute, where his students would include Disney studio animators for Bambi. Lebrun continued to produce paintings while teaching, and his first solo exhibition was organized by Donald Bear, then director of the Santa Barbara Museum of Art. Beginning in 1947, Lebrun spent three years working on over 200 drawings and paintings for the Crucifixion series, which culminated in an exhibition at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art.
In the late 1940s and 1950s, he continued to teach at the Jepson Institute in Los Angeles and at other institutions, including the Instituto Allende in San Miguel, Mexico from 1952 to 1954. In 1958, while teaching at Yale, Lebrun was invited by professor and art critic Peter Selz to create a mural for Pomona College. He completed his plans for the mural during his year-long teaching residency at the American Academy of Rome in 1959, and completed Genesis in 1960. Lebrun died from cancer in 1964.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter, muralist, and educator Rico Lebrun measure 5.3 linear feet and date from 1935 to 1975. Found within the papers are biographical materials; personal and business correspondence, including extensive correspondence between Lebrun and his gallery, Jacques Seligmann and Co.; writings, including illustrated notebooks; personal business records; printed material; 3 sketchbooks; and photographs of Lebrun, travels in Mexico, and his work.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1948-1962 (4 folders; Box 1, OV 10)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1935-1973 (1.7 linear feet; Boxes 1-2, OV 10)
Series 3: Writings, 1938-1964 (0.7 linear feet; Boxes 2-3)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1940-1964 (0.3 linear feet; Box 3, BV 7)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1940-1975 (0.8 linear feet; Box 3, BV 8-9)
Series 6: Artwork, circa 1950-1965 (3 folders; Box 3)
Series 7: Photographic Materials, 1950-1965 (1.6 linear feet; Boxes 4-6)
Jacques Seligmann & Co.; Educators--California--Los Angeles; Muralists--California--Los Angeles; Painters--California--Los Angeles; Painting, American; Photographs; Sketchbooks
- Biographical Materials, 1948-1962; Series 1; 4 Folders Box 1, OV 10
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical materials include a certificate from the National Academy of Design, citizenship records, curriculum vitae, and a transcript of an interview by Bill Gorman dating from 1962.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are arranged by document type.
  - Certificate, National Academy of Design, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Citizenship Records, 1948-1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Interview Transcript, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1935-1973; Series 2; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, OV 10
  Correspondence consists of letters to Lebrun regarding the exhibition, commission, and sales of his artwork, as well as correspondence from friends, colleagues, and family members. There is extensive chronological correspondence between Lebrun and his gallery, Jacques Seligmann and Co., and other correspondents of note include Julian Levi and Barry Robert Schachtman. Diagrams and plans for the mural Genesis can be found in correspondence with Pomona College. Letters of condolences to Lebrun's widow, Constance Lebrun, are filed at the end of the series.
  A selection of letters has retained alphabetical arrangement by sender. The remaining correspondence retains arrangement in chronological order.
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1952-1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Academy in Rome, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Federation of Arts, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Art Gallery of Toronto, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Art Students League, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ballet International, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ballet Theatre, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Boston Public Library, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Boston University, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Brice, William, circa 1950-1960 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bruggers, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - California State Board of Equalization, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Carnegie Institute, 1952-1964 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cober Gallery, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - de Cordova and Dana Museum, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - de Young Museum, 1952-1957 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Department of Municipal Art, City of Los Angeles, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Federman, Herrman, Stonehill, and Co., 1965 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Frank Perls Gallery, 1952-1957 (Box 1, Folder 23-25)
  - Fuegi, John, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Garibay, Roberto, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - GCA Gallery, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Goodrich, Lloyd, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Gorostiza, Celestino, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Grippi Gallery, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1935-1963 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Haskin, Don, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Langsner, Jules, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - L.A. County Museum, 1962-1968 (Box 1, Folder 35-36)
  - Meriden Gravure Company, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Mesches, Arnold, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - National Academy of Design, 1948-1963 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - New York Post Office, 1936-1941 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Newport Harbor Exhibition, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 42-43)
  - Obelisk Gallery, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Occidental College, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Patchen, Miriam, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Pearson, circa 1940-1960 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, 1953-1963 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Pomona College, 1956-1974 (Box 1, Folder 49-55)
  - Price, Vincent, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Princeton University Art Museum, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Sanchez, Horatio, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Sandoval, Carlos, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Selz, Peter, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Tejada, Julio, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - University of California Press, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - University of Southern California, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Worcester Art Museum, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Work Returned, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Work Out, 1958-1965 (Box 1, Folder 67-69)
  - Chronological, circa 1937-1963 (Box 1, Folder 70-74)
  - Chronological, 1938-1950 (Box 1, Folder 75-81)
  - Chronological, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 82-88)
  - Chronological, 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 1-11)
  - Chronological, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 12-20)
  - Chronological, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 21-28)
  - Chronological, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 29-34)
  - Chronological, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 35-43)
  - Chronological, 1966-1973 (Box 2, Folder 44-45)
    Oversized materials housed in OV 10.
  - Chronological, C.L. [Constance Lebrun], circa 1953-1965 (Box 2, Folder 46-47)
  - Chronological, C.L. [Constance Lebrun], 1953-1965 (Box 2, Folder 48-50)
  - Oversized Drawings from Box 2, Folder 44, 1966 (Box OV 10)
- Writings, 1938-1964; Series 3; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 2-3
  Writings consist of original illustrated manuscript/notebooks, a studio notebook, and exhibition guestbook registers dating from the 1950s. Typescripts of Lebrun's autobiography, notes on drawing, and general remarks on art and other topics that appear as poetry are also included.
  Typescript material has retained numerical ordering. The remaining materials are arranged by document type.
  - Autobiography (201-206), circa 1959 (Box 2, Folder 51-56)
  - Notes on Drawing (207-216), circa 1959 (Box 2, Folder 57-63)
  - Poetry (301-312), circa 1963 (Box 2, Folder 64-69)
  - Poetry, "Agricultural Period" (313), circa 1959-1963 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Poetry, "Capri" (314), circa 1963 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Poetry, "Splendor as Idea" (315), circa 1959-1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Poetry, "What Not to Do" (316), circa 1963 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Poetry, Untitled (317), circa 1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - General Remarks on Art (318), circa 1959-1963 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Guestbook, circa 1950-1960 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Guestbooks, 1951, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
  - Illustrated Manuscript, circa 1950-1960 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Illustrated Notebooks, circa 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 11-13)
  - Studio Notebook, circa 1938-1941 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Much of the writing is in Elaine Lebrun's handwriting.
  - Miscellaneous, 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Personal Business Records, 1940-1964; Series 4; 0.3 Linear feet Box 3, BV 7
  Personal business records consist of account book/ledgers and studio inventories of drawings and other works. There are also receipts, invoices, and correspondence detailing the sale, loan, and exhibition of his works.
  - Account Book, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Account Ledger, circa 1945-1949 (Box BV 7)
  - Inventory, Drawings, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Inventory, Studio, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Loans, Exhibitions, and Sales, 1940-1963 (Box 3, Folder 19-21)
- Printed Material, circa 1940-1975; Series 5; 0.8 Linear feet Box 3, BV 8-9
  Printed material includes clippings; exhibition announcements and catalogs; periodicals; and reproductions of works of art. Two books, Lebrun's Handbook on Deer, which was given to Disney studio animators working on the film Bambi, and Homage to Rico Lebrun, which was compiled by Lebrun's students, are included.
  - Book, Handbook on Deer, by Rico Lebrun, circa 1942 (Box BV 8)
  - Book, Homage to Rico Lebrun, 1964 (Box BV 9)
  - Clippings, circa 1950-1965 (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
  - Clippings, 1951-1963 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, circa 1940-1975 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1940-1975 (Box 3, Folder 26-33)
  - Periodicals, 1931-1962 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Reproductions of Works of Art, circa 1950-1965 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous, 1949-1957 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Artwork, circa 1950-1965; Series 6; 3 Folders Box 3
  Artwork consists of three sketchbooks of outlines, ideas, and pen and ink figure studies. Additional artwork can be found in the illustrated notebooks included in the Writings series.
  - Sketchbooks, circa 1950-1965 (Box 3, Folder 37-39)
- Photographic Materials, circa 1950-1965; Series 7; 1.6 Linear feet Boxes 4-6
  Photographic materials include Lebrun working on murals, models posing for works, and travel photos from Mexico that depict village scenes and images from a cattle slaughterhouse. There are also extensive copy prints, negatives, and glass plate transparencies of Lebrun's drawings and other works of art.
  Materials are arranged by subject and document type.
  - Photographs of Rico Lebrun Working on Mural, circa 1950 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Rico Lebrun and Models, circa 1950-1960 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Model for Genesis Mural at Pomona College, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photographs and Negatives of Models, circa 1950-1965 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Color Slides and Transparencies of Travel, circa 1955-1965 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Color Slides and Photographs of Travel, circa 1950-1965 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Travel, circa 1950-1965 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
  - Photographs of Exhibition Installations, circa 1955-1965 (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
  - Photographs and Negatives of Exhibition Installations, circa 1955-1965 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Photographs and Negatives of Exhibition Installations, 1956-1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Photographs and Negatives of Exhibition Installation, Newport, California, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Photographs of Drawings/Sketches, Animals and Plants, circa 1950-1965 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Photographs of Drawings/Sketches, Paintings, circa 1950-1965 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Photographs of Drawings/Sketches, Men, circa 1950-1965 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Photographs of Drawings/Sketches, Women, circa 1950-1965 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Photographs of Mixed Media, circa 1950-1965 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Photographs of Murals, circa 1950-1965 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Photographs and Negatives of Sculptures, circa 1950-1965 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, circa 1950-1965 (Box 4, Folder 21-23)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, circa 1950-1965 (Box 4, Folder 24-28)
    Includes copy stand prints for (10-##), (16-##), (17-##), (18-##), and (19-##).
  - Photographs of Works of Art, circa 1950-1965 (Box 4, Folder 29-36)
    Includes copy stand prints for (20-##), (21-##), (22-##), (23-##), (24-##), (25-##), (26-##), and (29-##).
  - Photographs of Works of Art, circa 1950-1965 (Box 4, Folder 37-40)
    Includes copy stand prints for (30-##), (31-##), (32-##), and (34-##).
  - Color Transparencies of Works of Art, circa 1955-1965 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Negatives of Works of Art, circa 1950-1965 (Box 4, Folder 42-43)
  - Negatives of Works of Art, circa 1950-1965 (Box 5, Folder 1-6)
    Includes copy stand prints for (7-##), (10-##), (16-##), (17-##), (18-##), and (19-##).
  - Negatives of Works of Art, circa 1950-1965 (Box 5, Folder 7-15)
    Includes copy stand prints for (20-##), (21-##), (22-##), (23-##), (24-##), (25-##), (26-##), (29-##), and (30-##).
  - Negatives of Works of Art, circa 1950-1965 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
    Includes copy stand prints for (31-##), (32-##), and (34-##).
  - Black and White Glass Plate Transparencies of Works of Art, circa 1950-1965 (Box 6, Folder 4-6)
  - Color Glass Plate Transparencies of Works of Art, circa 1950-1965 (Box 6, Folder 7-10)